(
"ai_sub_version": "3.6.0",
"generated_at": "2026-10-10T13:46:31.045569",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"service_tier": null,
"service_tier_subtitles": null,
"service_tier_lyrics": null,
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
のっじゃあ〜！
Nochiah~!
んー
Hmm...
あらあら めらめら あっちちめら〜！
Ara ara, mela mela, achichi mela~!
ホロライブ遊び隊！ゴリラクターン等のヒケシヤサランマンダあっちちめらだのっじゃあ〜！
Hololive Asobi-tai! Gorilla-ctan and Hikeshiya Saranmanda achichi mela danocchia~!
今日は…
Today...
なんて言うゲームをやろかというと
What kind of game are we going to play, you ask?
よいしょ。今日は何というゲームをやると…
Let's see. Today, what kind of game are we playing...
スパゲットーというゲームで遊んでいくのじゃ。
We're going to play a game called "Spaghet."
知らないゲーム。なんか、名前だけ知ってるゲーム、
A game I don't know. Just a game whose name I know,
名前だけ知ってるゲーム、なんかホロライブで流行ってるらしいという知識のみ。
a game whose name I only know because I heard it's trending in Hololive.
ホロライブで流行っていって…えっとね、ふぶき先輩にね、
It's been trending in Hololive... Um, Fubuki-senpai
いただいたんだが…
gave it to me, but...
あの、ふぶき先輩がゲームの説明してくれたから読むのじゃ。
Um, Fubuki-senpai explained the game to me, so I'll read it.
メッセージでね、ちょっと待って、大きくする。えっとね…
In a message... wait, let me make it bigger. Um...
あなたはスパゲティーが好きですか？それは結構。でしたりますます好きになりますよ！
"Do you like spaghetti? That's great. If so, you'll love it even more!
とても簡単！スパゲティーを温めるだけのとっても楽しい世界があなたを待っています。
Super simple! A super fun world awaits you, just warming up spaghetti.
初心者でも安心アットホームなスパゲティーです！
It's a cozy spaghetti for beginners too!
これであなたもスパゲティーのことが好きになります今すぐダウンロード！
With this, you'll love spaghetti too! Download now!"
で、そのコマンドって何なのだじゃ？コマンドって何なのだじゃ？わしそれ知らない。
And what is that "command"? What is that command? I don't know that.
わしそれ知らない。配信で触れてもいいやつ？なんか知らないミームってさ、あの、ワンチャンさ配信で、あの言うちゃダメなさ、あのミームである可能性があるからさ、ちょっとすごい怖いんだけど。
I don't know that. Is it okay to touch on stream? There's a chance it might be a meme you shouldn't say on stream, so I'm pretty scared.
平気？いいやつ？あ、映画？
Is it fine? A good thing? Oh, a movie?
映画？のじゃのじゃのじゃ。なるほどのじゃ。
A movie? Nochianochianochia. I see, nochia.
なるのののじゃ。映画か。
Narunononochia. A movie, huh.
よかった。なんか、あの、やばいネタかと思った。やばいネタかと思った。
Good. I thought it was some dangerous material. I thought it was dangerous material.
コマンドって映画のこうぶんなんじゃの？
Is "Commando" a quote from a movie?
なんかその、Twitterでこれツイートした時のインリツにも確か、なんかコマンドこうぶん、みたいな書いてあってなんだろって思ってた。
I was wondering what it was because I remember something like "Commando quote" written in the quote-tweets when I tweeted this on Twitter.
なんだろって思ったけど調べたらこのパスタの、もしかしてこのパスタのゲームのネタバレになる可能性があると思って…うん。
I wondered what it was, but when I looked it up, I thought it might be a spoiler for this pasta game, so... yeah.
パスタのゲームがどういうゲームかのネタバレになっちゃうかなと思ってね、見るのをねやめ調べるのをねやめましたのじゃ。
Thinking it might spoil what kind of game the pasta game is, I stopped looking at it, you see.
よいしょ。
Yoisho.
のじゃ！
Noja!
ニコニコ初のミームは知らない。
I don't know the first Niconico memes.
うん。
Yeah.
なんか、ニコニコ動画撮ってないから
Like, I didn't record Niconico Douga,
知らないわし、ニコニコ動画のミーム。
so I don't know Niconico Douga memes.
なんて知らないかと言うと、あの、インターネット始めて、
Why I don't know is, um, I started the internet,
あの、だから、あの、良くないことが起きて、
and, um, so, um, bad things happened,
家特定されて、あの、父と母に拾われて、
my house got doxxed, um, and my dad and mom picked me up.
で、父と母に拾われたときに、
And when my dad and mom picked me up,
なんか、わしがまた掲示板とか危ないサイトを
like, if I looked at bulletin boards
見たら、良くないみたいな。
or dangerous sites again, it'd be bad.
そう。なんか、わしの、
Right. Like, my,
なんかすんのセキュリティ、なんて言うの？
like, that security, what is it called?
なんて言うんだっけ、あの、フィルタリング？
What was it called, um, filtering?
フィルタリングみたいなのので、
Like filtering, it was set to
めちゃ厳しい設定にされて、
super strict settings,
だから、その、そっから厳しい設定にされちゃったから、
so, since it got set to strict settings from there,
ニコニコ動画もYouTubeも、
I couldn't watch Niconico Douga or YouTube
その時期を全部見れてないのじゃん。そう。
for all of that era, you know. Right.
そう、キッズフィルター、
Yeah, kids filter,
そう、キッズフィルターかけられて、
yeah, kids filter applied,
キッズフィルターかけられてガチ何も見れなくて、
kids filter applied and I genuinely couldn't see anything,
え、だからニコニコ動画も、あの、それの対象となって、
so, Niconico Douga was also, um, subject to that,
そう、ニコニコ動画もYouTubeも見れてないじゃん、だから。
so I couldn't watch Niconico Douga or YouTube either, you see.
そう、YouTubeもダメだった。
Yeah, YouTube was no good either.
それほどわしが危ないことをしたということ。
It means I did something dangerous to that extent.
のじゃ。
Indeed.
そう。だから、その、イニシエのニコニコ動画は、
Right. So, um, ancient Niconico Douga,
全然通ってないけど、でも最近は見るよ、ニコニコ。
I didn't go through at all, but I watch it recently, Niconico.
ぼくはこれボカロイドコレクションのときだけ、
I only watch Niconico Douga a lot
ニコニコ動画めちゃ見るよ、わし。
during the Vocaloid Collection, me.
ボカロ曲を聞くために、ボカロPさんがニコニコ動画にさ、
To listen to Vocaloid songs, Vocaloid P-s post videos
先に動画上げるからさ、早く聞きたいから、
on Niconico Douga first, and because I want to listen quickly,
ニコニコ動画で見れるのじゃん。
I watch them on Niconico Douga.
最近のニコニコってどうなの？
What are recent Niconicos like?
え、知らない。ぼくはこれのことしか知らないわしは。
Huh, I don't know. I only know this stuff.
それ以外のカテゴリーはあんま見ないから、あまり詳しくないのじゃ。
I don't really look at other categories, so I'm not very familiar.
スマホ取り上げられなかった？
Weren't your smartphone taken away?
いや、あれはもうほぼ取り上げといても過言ではないのじゃ。
No, it's no exaggeration to say it was practically taken away.
なんか、あの、キッズ携帯みたいな、電話できないキッズ携帯みたいなのを持たされてた記憶あり。
I remember being made to carry a kids' phone where you couldn't make calls.
え、そう、ついにガラケーに回り回したなのだじゃん。
Oh right, it finally went full circle back to a flip phone!
わし400歳なのに、キッズ携帯を持たされてた。
Even though I'm 400 years old, I was made to have a kids' phone.
防犯ブザーみたいな機能がついてるキッズ携帯を持たされていた記憶あり。
I remember having a kids' phone with a crime prevention buzzer-like function.
外で電波がつながらないSIMが入ってないiPhoneを持たされていた記憶あり。
I remember having an iPhone with no outside signal and no SIM card.
Wi-Fiが繋がってるとこしか使えないけど、使えるサイトも制限されてるみたいな。
You could only use it on Wi-Fi, but usable sites were restricted too.
ほぼたまごっちですのじゃ。
It's practically a Tamagotchi.
ガラケーと変わらんのじゃ。
It's no different from a flip phone.
心配だったっぽい。心配だったっぽい。
Seems like they were worried. Seems like they were worried.
わしがネットで危ないことするから、この子が成長するまでスマホを持たせてはいけないと思われたっぽい。
Because I do dangerous things online, it seemed like they thought I shouldn't have a smartphone until I grew up.
反動で今ドッパマンダになってるのじゃ。ドッパマンダでしょ、じゃあ。
As a reaction, now I've become Dappamanda. Dopamanda, right?
当時、だからさ、結構さ、ニコニコ動画とかインターネットミームとか、
At that time, so, pretty much, Niconico Douga and internet memes,
わしが禁止されてた時期に流行ったコンテンツを知ってる人が羨ましいのじゃ。
I envy people who know content popular when I was banned.
反動というのは、誰にでも訪れますのじゃ。
Reactions come to everyone.
友達と話が合わなくんなんなかった。
I couldn't talk in sync with friends anymore.
ええ？友達？
Eh? Friends?
のじゃあ、えど、なんか？
Nojaa, Edo, something?
その… その時めちゃくちゃ仲いい子が…
...That in that time, we didn't have many...
いなかった。
good friends around.
その… 要はそのわしが… あのキッズフィルタリングみたいなさされてた頃は、やっぱ人間低学年だしょ…
You know, when Washi was doing "kids filtering" or whatever back then,
人間で言うところの小学生とか中学生の頃じゃろ?
human-wise, we were elementary or middle schoolers, right?
え、その頃って結構なんか… 見た目で迫害みたいなあったから、角とか尻尾とか生えてたし、わし…
Back then, appearance-wise, kids bullied each other, so people with horns or tails...
なんかあんまりなじめなかった記憶。
Well, I couldn't really fit in, I remember.
さあ、楽しいゲームするか！
Let's play a fun game!
楽しいゲームするのじゃ！
す、スパゲッティのアットホームな… アットホームなスパゲッティのゲーム…
A game about at-home... at-home spaghetti...
アットホームなスパゲッティのゲームするのじゃ。うん。のじゃ。うん。
An at-home spaghetti game, let's play that. Yeah.
なんか、うん、そ、そ、そうなのじゃ。
Alright.
よいしょ。よいしょ。パスタ…
Boiling...
冷めちゃう？
getting cold?
えっと、えっと、ちょっと待つのじゃ。うん。
Um...
あ、でも、でも、でも、補足、補足、1点補足。
Oh, but wait, a minor detail, 1.1 addition:
でも、あのー… わしが人間に対抗する術を身につけてからは、
Once Washi acquired ways to deal with humans,
あの、と… 友達とかもでき始めたし、から、あの…
friends and stuff started to appear, so...
安心してほしいのじゃ。
please rest assured.
うん、安心してほしいのじゃ。
Please rest assured.
パスタ、パスタ食べる、パスタ食べる。
Pasta, eat pasta, eat pasta.
えーっとね、
Let's see...
そう、どうやらアットホームな… あ、アットホームなスパゲッティってなんだ？
So, apparently it's an "at-home" -- Wait, what is an "at-home spaghetti" game?
アットホームなスパゲッティらしい。
Apparently it's an "at-home spaghetti" game.
アットホームなスパゲッティ、初心者でも安心… 安心ってなんだ？
An "at-home spaghetti" -- "Safe for beginners"? Wait, what does "safe" mean?
あんまりそのスパゲッティを形容する言葉として…
I don't usually hear "spaghetti" described with words like...
初心者でも、ま、初心者でも安心はゲームに対してかな？
"beginner-friendly." Well, "beginner-friendly" probably applies to the game.
うん、ゲームに対しての…併用する言葉なのかな？
It's probably a word used for the game, right?
アットホーム言わない… 言わない気がする。
It feels like they wouldn't say "at-home."
から、なんだろ、吹雪先輩ミームが使いたかったのかな？
So, I wonder if Fubuki-senpai wanted to use a meme?
わし、そのコマンドミーム知らないから、
Since Washi doesn't know command memes,
なんか、初心者でも安心アットホームなみたいなのも、ミームの言葉なのかな？
I wonder if "beginner-friendly, at-home-like" is also a meme phrase?
そこまで含めてこうぶんみたいな感じなのかな？
Like, is it an idiom that includes all of that?
ごめんね、ミームの元ネタが分からないからさ、どこまでがミームのあれなのか分かんなくて。
I don't know how far the meme goes, so I'm not really sure.
ふむふむふむ。
Mm-hm, mm-hm, mm-hm.
でもわし、わしの知ってる人間豆知識披露していい？
But Washi -- can I share some human trivia that Washi knows?
わしの知ってる人間豆知識なんだけど、あの人間の職場？ なんか、仕事？雇用？ 雇用募集みたいなのの、で「アットホーム」って言葉が書かれてるのは「アットホームじゃない」って聞いたのじゃ。
It's human trivia I know, but about human workplaces, like, jobs, job hunting, and stuff -- I heard that the phrase "at-home" actually means it's *not* at-home.
それだけ知ってるのじゃ。
That's all I know.
人間が使う「アットホーム」って言葉は、なんかすごい空気が悪いらしい、との噂。
When humans use the word "at-home," it apparently has a really bad vibe to it, or so the rumor goes.
わしが人間と関わってる間に身につけた豆知識。
That's the trivia Washi picked up while interacting with humans.
ていうことはって何？ 空気悪いのこのスパゲッティ？ 人間関係とかある感じ？ このゲーム、このゲーム人間関係あるのじゃ？
So what does that mean?! Is this "at-home" spaghetti game giving off bad vibes? Does it have human relations stuff in it?
ん？
Hmm?
対人ゲーか？ 対人ゲーか？
Like a psychological horror game?
うん。
Mm-hm.
でもなんか、やっぱ新人に、新人にさ、ゲームくれる吹雪先輩めっちゃ優しいのじゃ。
Fubuki-senpai is so kind for giving a game to a newbie like me, right?
めっちゃ優しいのじゃ！
She's so kind!
から、あの、嬉しい、ありがとうございますって思うのじゃ。
So I'm like, "Thank you so much!"
あとオカユ先輩にもね、あのゲームをね、いただいていてね、あの、タンポポのやつとかいただいてるから、それもまたやりたいなって思ってますのじゃ。
And Ookami-senpai also gave me a game, you know? Like the dandelion one, so I'm thinking I wanna play that again too!
先輩優しいのじゃ！
Seniors are so kind!
まだわし新人だし、あんまりお話ししたこともないのにゲームを送ってくれるなんて、えだってゲームって結構好きな人にしか送らないよね？
I'm still a newbie, and we haven't talked much, yet she sent me a game. I mean, people usually only send games to people they really like, right?
え、じゃない？ なんか、結構ゲームを送るってことは親密度さ、高めなんじゃない？ 高めなんじゃない？
Right? Sending a game means their intimacy level is pretty high, right?
あの、お近づきのしるしに的さ、仲良くなりたいって思ってるんじゃない、わしと？ねえ？
Like, it's a sign that you're getting close, you want to get along better with Washi, right?
えだからすごい、すごい嬉しくて、そう、すごい連絡いただいたときはめちゃくちゃ嬉しくて、楽しみなのじゃ！嬉しいのじゃ！
So I was super, super happy, and when she gave me that great message, I was so happy, I'm looking forward to it! I'm so happy!
じゃあ、ゲームやるお部屋に行こうかの。
Let's head to the gaming room.
よいしょ。
Here we go!
よいしょお！
のちゃあ！
Nocha!
スパゲッティ。
Spaghet.
音量、どれぐらいがいいかな。
Let's see, how's the volume?
ちょっとした音しか入ってないけど。
There's only a little bit of sound.
音量もっと上げるか。
Let's turn the volume up.
オーディオボリューム。
Audio volume...
これぐらいにしとくか。
Let's put it around here.
これぐらいでいい？
Is this good?
ちっちゃい？
Too quiet?
音ちっちゃい？
Is the audio quiet?
どうかあの、開始してみないと
Let's see, I won't know until I start it...
ま、確かに、割とこのちっちゃめの音じゃとね、あんまわかんないよね。
Well, true, with this relatively small sound,
you can't really tell.
よいしょ、よいしょ。
Heave-ho, heave-ho.
いい感じ？
Feeling good?
え、でもさ、もしなんかさ、この、このなんか、これ気になってて、何これ？
Wait, but like, what's with this?
This has been bothering me. What is this?
ちょっと画面ちっちゃいの使ってるからもう見えないんだけど。
I'm using a small screen
so I can't really see it.
目が赤い。
Her eyes are red.
目が赤いのがいる。
There's one with red eyes.
何？これはまた別？映画とか？
What? Is this another one?
A movie or something?
謎なのだじゃん。
It's a mystery.
広告？広告的なあれか。広告だからあんま気にしなくていいか。
An ad? Is that an ad thing? It's an ad,
so I guess I don't need to worry about it.
よし、じゃあ一旦プレイを押してみるのじゃ。
Alright, then I'll try
pressing "Play" for now.
よいしょ。
Heave-ho.
ほろほろ。
Hmm, hmm.
え？手と部屋かな？キッチンだ。
Huh? Is this my hands and a room?
It's a kitchen.
キッチンのノラじゃ広い。え、暗い。広くて高め。
The kitchen is pretty big. Uh, it's dark.
It's spacious and high-end.
贅沢めのおうち、贅沢めのおうち、Look at the spaghet to see the slap sequence. Slap the spaghet... slapって？
A luxury home, a luxury home... Look at the spaghet to see the slap sequence.
Slap the spaghet... What does "slap" mean?
叩く？
Hit?
Slapって、わしの思ってるslapと一緒？
Does "slap" mean
what I think it means?
え、英語の意味が違う？Slapって叩く？叩く以外の意味があるのじゃ？
Wait, do English words have different meanings?
Does "slap" mean hit? Are there other meanings?
調理系で聞いたのじゃ。
I heard it in a cooking context.
え、え、Slap the spaghet by the clicking the correct mouse button in the sequence.
"Slap the spaghet by clicking
the correct mouse button in the sequence."
マウスを押しして操作する系か。
So it's operated by clicking the mouse?
マウスのボタンを押して...
Press the mouse button and...
マウスのボタンを押して、えー操作します。Complete sequences to keep the spaghet warm.
Press the mouse button and... operate it.
"Complete sequences to keep the spaghet warm."
ほう？温める？
Hmm? Warm it up?
ほう、これわしの英語が合ってる？なんかスパゲッティを叩いて温めるって書いてない？
Hmm, is my English correct? Doesn't it say
to warm up the spaghetti by slapping it?
気のせい？
Am I imagining things?
摩擦的な？人間ってそういう能力があるのじゃ？
Friction-like?
Do humans have that kind of ability?
え、人間！人間って手でさ、パスタ叩いたら温められるの？わしそれ知らない！
Wait, humans! Can humans warm up pasta
just by slapping it? I didn't know that!
え、人間って結構万能なのでは？
Wait, aren't humans pretty versatile?
Try to complete the first sequence.
ほう、これはレフト、ライト、レフトか。Slapって出てくるけど。Slapって出てくるけど。
Hmm, so it's left, right, left?
"Slap" pops up. "Slap" pops up, but...
え！？
Eh!?
ぼよん言うたよ。ぼよんゆうたのじゃ。
It went "boing."
It literally went "boing."
何これ？どういうこ...ん？
What is this? What does th... Huh?
これで温まるのじゃ？
Does this warm it up?
一旦チュートリアルやるか。え、L？
Let's do the tutorial first. Uh, L?
手汚れちゃうよ。
Your hands are gonna get dirty.
人間はこういうことができるのじゃ？
Can humans do stuff like this?
熱エネルギー的なのじゃ？
Is it like thermal energy?
なんか左上に寒いマークと熱いマークがある。これで温めてることになるのじゃ？
There's a cold mark and a hot mark in the upper left.
Does this mean I'm warming it up?
Each completed sequence increases the temperature meter above. あ、左上の温度が叩くと温度が上がるらしい。
"Each completed sequence increases the temperature meter above."
Ah, hitting it increases the temperature.
温めってそういうこと？レンジとかじゃないのじゃ？
Is that what warming up means?
It's not a microwave or anything?
レンジは最近の話なのはじゃ。この時代は手で温めてたのじゃ？
Microwaves are a recent thing.
In this era, did they warm it up by hand?
If the temperature meter gets too low, the spaghet will freeze? スパゲッティ凍っちゃうらしい。
"If the temperature meter gets too low, the spaghet will freeze."
Apparently the spaghetti freezes.
みんなそうしてる？あ、みんなそうしてるんだ。知らなかった。レンジが古い？
Everyone does that? Ah, everyone does that.
I didn't know. The microwave is old?
でも手汚れちゃうよのじゃ。
But your hands will get dirty.
え、でこ、えでこ、コアラはゲームだから、なんか温めないと凍っちゃうらしい。凍るって何？簡単に作るっていいのじゃ？
Wait, but Koala is a game, so if you don't warm it up,
it freezes. Wait, can you freeze pasta that easily?
If that happens, it's all over. すべてが終わりだって。どういうこと？本気すぎ、ゼロ、パスタの温めに。
"If that happens, it's all over." It says everything is over.
What does that mean? So serious, zero, for warming up pasta.
Press A ていうか コンティニュー。
Press A... I mean, continue.
のじゃ？
Huh?
なんか思ってたのと違うのじゃ なんか あのクッキングゲーみたいな...
That's not what I expected. Something like a cooking game...
クッキングシミュレーター的なのを想像して来ましたのじゃ。
I imagined something like a cooking simulator.
なんか あの 湯切りして パスタを何分茹でて湯切りして あの ソースかけて あの 客に提供するみたいな。
Like, draining the pasta, boiling it for a few minutes,
draining it, putting sauce on it, and serving it to customers.
なんか えっ ゲームってさ そういうさ のあるよね？ なんか パスタシミュレーターみたいなのじゃ。
I mean, games have things like that, right?
Like a pasta simulator.
Let's cooking?
人間はこれが普通なのじゃ？
Is this normal for humans?
人間はこういうのが好きなの？
Do humans like this kind of thing?
ええ。
Right.
はい インコレクト えー インコモウ 間違ったマウスを押してしまうと マウスボタンを押してしまうと えー You'll punch the spaghetti ほー
Yeah, incorrect, um, incom— If you click the wrong mouse button,
um, "You'll punch the spaghetti." Oh.
あー これはあれか？ あの ゲーム性じゃ。
Ah, is this part of it? Um, game mechanics.
なるほど 間違ったボタン押しちゃうと あの 叩くじゃなくて 殴るになってしまうらしいのじゃ。
I see, if you press the wrong button,
instead of patting, it turns into punching.
This will cause the temperature to drop faster. あ 殴ると 本当叩かなきゃいけないのを殴ってしまうと あの 温度が急激に落ちてしまって冷えやすくなっちゃうのかな。
This will cause the temperature to drop faster.
Ah, if you punch it instead of patting it, the temperature drops rapidly...
Complete the next four sequences. えー ライト ライト ライト
Complete the next four sequences.
Um, right, right, right.
な 何これ？ ペチョンペチョン言ってる。 ぺ ぺ ペチョンペチョン言ってるけど。
W-What is this? It's making squish-squish noises.
It's making squish-squish noises.
音ゲーなのじゃ？
Is this a rhythm game?
音ゲーなのじゃ？ ん？
Is this a rhythm game? Hm?
In the top right corner... これほうな オザスクリーン there is a visibility meter.
In the top right corner... over here on the screen,
"there is a visibility meter."
なんかあるよね 右にね。This meter fills when never unwanted spectator watches you. どういうこと？
There is one on the right, right?
"This meter fills whenever an unwanted spectator watches you." What does that mean?
何が見てるの？
What is watching?
If the meter fills completely, you lose. 負けます。
If the meter fills completely, you lose. You lose.
何？ 調理ゲーと聞いていいる。 調理ゲーと言っていますのじゃ。
What? I heard this was a cooking game.
They're saying it's a cooking game.
ホロオリ？
Holo-ori?
これが？ 競合なのじゃ？
Is this? Competition?
自家コンテンツの競合コンテンツですのじゃ。 それを回してるのじゃ？
It's competing content of our own content.
Are they spinning that?
それはいいの？
Is that okay?
えー レッツ えー avoid that, look down at the arrow. 左クリック when you see hide to crouch behind the corner. あ 隠れられるんだ。
Um, let's, um, "avoid that, look down at the arrow."
Left click "when you see 'HIDE' to crouch behind the corner." Ah, you can hide.
何が 見てるの わしよ？ 何が見 てるの？
What is looking at me? What is looking?
なんか何かがわしのことを見てるっぽくて なんか隠れたりもできるらしい。
It seems like something is watching me,
and apparently you can hide too.
Left click when you see hide. Hideどうやってやんじゃ？
Left click when you see hide.
How do you do hide?
ちょっといまとこない。 いまとこなぽい。
It's not here right now. Seems like it's not here yet.
あ あった。 なるほど 下に行くとハイド。 下に行くと隠れられるっぽい。
Ah, there it is. I see, going down is hide.
Going down seems to let you hide.
誰から隠れたらなのじゃ？えー、While down here, you can't be seen by anyone on the other side of the counter. 向こう側にいる人の誰からも見られなくなります。 ここに 隠れてるからね。
Who are we hiding from? Um, "While down here, you can't be seen by anyone on the other side of the counter."
You won't be seen by anyone on the other side. Because you're hiding here.
どういうこと？
What do you mean?
これな 何 何をするゲームなのじゃ？To stand, look up at the arrow on the edge of the counter. Counter, left click when you see stand up. オッケー スタンドアップ。
What kind of game is this? "To stand, look up at the arrow on the edge of the counter."
Counter, left click when you see "STAND UP." Okay, stand up.
ふむふむ。In the event that there is a threat on this side of the counter, you need to hide on the other side. なるほど。
I see. "In the event that there is a threat on this side of the counter, you need to hide on the other side."
I see.
また別のとこに隠れる必要もあるらしい。To do so, look at the arrow ahead of you, on the opposite side of the counter. 反対側にも隠れますよと。
It seems you also need to hide in other places. "To do so, look at the arrow ahead of you, on the opposite side of the counter."
You hide on the opposite side as well.
ジャンプアクロス！ジャンプアクロス？ 飛んで逃げられるのじゃ？
Jump across! Jump across? Can you fly away to escape?
ほう。Try it out, try to return to from the side, look up the arrow on the edge of the counter and left click when you see jump back. Press N, when you are back behind the original side of the counter...
Ho. "Try it out, try to return to from the side, look up the arrow on the edge of the counter and left click when you see 'JUMP BACK.'
Press N, when you are back behind the original side of the counter..."
何から隠れてるの？
What are we hiding from?
なんか 逃げ要素ありということ。
It means there's an escape element to it.
逃げ要素あり。 ほう。
An escape element. Ho.
アクションゲーム。
An action game.
まあ やってみるか。
Well, let's try it.
はい。This concludes a tutorial. To view this information again, you can enable it in the settings menu. Press A to cross. はい。
Right. "This concludes the tutorial. To view this information again, you can enable it in the Settings menu.
Press A to close." Right.
まあ大体 大体わかったのじゃ。 大体言いたいことはわかった。
Well, I mostly understood. I more or less got what they wanted to say.
やってみるか
Let's give it a try.
Jump across
何？何？何？何？
What? What? What? What?
何何何何何！
What is this?!
何起きた？何起きた？
What just happened?!
何？何？何？待って、何？
What? What? Wait, what?!
何？
What?
なんかすごい音する！絶対動いちゃダメじゃん！
That's a crazy sound! I definitely can't move!
何？な、
What? Wh—
え、パスワード？
Huh, a password?
え、なんでこう、なんでこんな暗いの？え？
Huh? Why is it so dark? Huh?
あ、もしミスターっぽい？
Ah, is this Mr. ...?
何？何？何の音？何の音？
What? What? What is that sound?
何？何の音？何の音がしてんのじゃ？
What? What is that sound?!
な、ぐ、ぐわ、なんだぐしゃった！う、のじゃー！
Gah, it got all squished! Ugh, no way!
なん、今何が起きてる？
Wh— What's happening right now?!
なんかすごい音する！ホラーゲームみたいな音する！
There's a crazy sound! It sounds like a horror game!
ホラーゲームみたいな音するのじゃ！ね、ど、どぅおーって音する！何？
It sounds like a horror game! Hey, it's making a whooshing sound! What?!
うわー！
Whoa!
たすけて！たすけて！たすけて！
Help! Help! Help!
やばい！なんか全滅しちゃった！
No way! I totally got wiped out!
全滅しちゃった！
I got wiped out!
何！？な、なのじゃー！何！？
What?! No way! What?!
これ映っていいやつ？
Is it okay for this to be shown?
なんか、なんか出しちゃった！
I somehow... brought something out!
なんか出たのじゃ！なんか出た！なんか出た！
Something came out! Something came out!
のじゃ！？
No way?!
何！？待って、何のゲーム？ん？
What?! Wait, what kind of game is this?
おや？
Huh?
ほ、ほら？
H-Hold on?
え、これホラーなのじゃ？
Eh, is this a horror game?
これ、これクッキングゲームじゃない？
Isn't this... a cooking game?
これクッキングゲームじゃない？もしかして。
Isn't this a cooking game, by any chance?
びっくりしたー！
That scared me!
風邪先輩？
Fubuki-senpai?
風邪先輩ワシのと仲良くなりたいからゲームを送ってくれたんじゃないの？
Didn't Fubuki-senpai send me this game because they want to get along with me?
風邪先輩ワシのこと嫌い？
Does Fubuki-senpai hate me?
何？の、のじゃ！？な、のじゃ！？
What? No- No way?! No, no way?!
い,一旦水飲んで落ち着いて、いい？
C-Can I drink some water and calm down?
心臓がバクバクしてて…心臓がバクバクしてて…
My heart is pounding... My heart is pounding...
のじゃ…
No way...
これ洗礼なのじゃ？
Is this a baptism?
これ洗礼？
あ、洗礼ってそういう…
Ah, so a baptism is like that...
洗礼って…
A baptism...
あの、被害者を増やすためにある？
Is it meant to... increase the number of victims?
そこ知れぬ人間の悪意？いや、キツネなのじゃ。
That bottomless human malice? No, it's a fox.
のじゃ？
No way?
え、すごい心臓バクバクしてる。びび、びっくりしたー！
Wh-My heart is pounding so much. I-I was so surprised!
え、ちょ、教えてほしいんだけどさ、
Um, hey, I want you to tell me, but,
これは、パスタを叩き続ければいいわけじゃない？逃げ、隠れたりもしなきゃいけない？
this just means I have to keep pounding the pasta? Do I need to run and hide?
いつかく、ん？いつ隠れるのがいいの？
When hi-, hmm? When is it best to hide?
なんか、ちゅ、パニックになっちゃって。
I somehow... pa-, got all panicked.
一旦もう一回やるか。
Let's try it again.
叩きながら隠れる？叩きながら隠れなきゃいけない？
Hide while pounding? Do I have to hide while pounding?
あの、目が、あの、目のゲージが、どうなってる？マックスになったら来る？
Um, the eye gauge... what's happening? Does it come when it reaches max?
テレビを見るといい？
Is it good to watch TV?
テレビ？
TV?
カッティングナイス…
Cutting nice...
何？
What?
テレビを見るといいって言ったよ？
You said it's good to watch TV, right?
Jump across
テレビを見るといいって言った。テレビ見えない。
You said watch TV. I can't see the TV.
テレビ見えない。
I can't see the TV.
テレビ死がくれる。Stay away from goalと？
TV gives death. 'Stay away from goal'?
Jump across
え？どういうこと？
Huh? What does that mean?
うわあー！
Whoa!
ねえ、嘘！ねえ、Stay！
Hey, no way! Hey, Stay!
うううーーー！
Uuuuuuu!
どうしよう...
What should I do...?
今は... 今は本当はどうしなきゃいけなかった？
Right now... what was I actually supposed to do?
今は... カウントを取り替えなきゃ...
Right now... I need to reset the count...
なんか頭がごちゃごちゃ、のじゃ。
My head is all mixed up...
お化け？
A ghost?
ん？さっきと違うお化けだった？それもわかんなかった、のじゃ。
Hm? Was that a different ghost than before? I didn't even realize.
さっきと違うやつだった？反対側に... のじゃ。
Was it a different one from before? On the other side...
暇があったら叩く。ゴールデンが来たら飛び越える。
If you have time, slap. When the Golden comes, jump over.
足音が聞こえたらすすぐに飛び越える。
When you hear footsteps, jump over immediately.
あ、数種類いる。ゲーム性... ゲーム性...
Ah, there are several types. The gameplay... the gameplay...
キャラによって動きが違う。
The movements differ by character.
ホラーげやん。
It's a horror game.
音... 音怖い、のじゃ。
The sound... The sound is scary...
ちょ、もう1回やるか。
Hold on, let's go again.
テレビ見る。
Watch TV.
あ、テレビ。
Ah, TV.
何？テレビ、テレビ見る、テレビ見る、テレビ見る。
What? TV, look at TV, look at TV, look at TV.
見えない。
Can't see it.
ちょ、テレビ見えない、のじゃ。
Wait, I can't see the TV.
テレビ見えない。テレビ何も乗ってない。
Can't see the TV. There's nothing on the TV.
あ、あった。ステイ・アウェイ・フロム...
Ah, there it is. Stay away from...
えっ、ジャンプアクロス？こういうこと？こういうこと？
Eh, jump across? Like this? Like this?
いいんじゃない？
Isn't this good?
上手なんじゃない？
Aren't I doing well?
あ、いいんじゃない？
Ah, isn't this good?
え、き、き、き、き、来た、お前ら！来た、来た！お前馬鹿野郎！来た、来たのじゃ！
Eh, it's here, you guys! It's here! You idiot! It's here!
なんて？え？飛べてたじゃん！飛べてたじゃん！
What? Eh? I jumped! I jumped!
飛べてたじゃん！ねえ、飛べてって言われた！
I jumped! Hey, I was told I jumped!
コメづらいと飛べて終わるのじゃ。何？嘘つき！改めます。
It ends when you're hard to comment on. What? Liar! I take it back.
え？ん？早すぎた？
Eh? Hm? Was it too early?
え、わしが悪いのか、今。
Eh, is it my fault this time?
今わしが悪い？早すぎる？
Is it my fault now? Too early?
のじゃあ...
Noh...
早い！タイ... タイミング？
Too fast! Ti... Timing?
出てから飛ぶ？足音、あ...
Jump after it appears? Footsteps, ah...
バカが言うとか言ってごめんな、のじゃ。
Sorry for saying you were an idiot, noh.
あの... 達席良くないのじゃ。タイミングゲー？
Umm... My seat isn't good. A timing game?
音ゲー？こんなとこでも？引きつけてからよける。
A rhythm game? Even in a place like this? Lure them in and dodge.
のじゃあ。
Noh.
なるほど、音を聞く。えっと、怖い音を大きくすると、ホラーゲームみたいな音する。
I see, listen to the sound. Um, making scary sounds louder makes it sound like a horror game.
怖い、のじゃ。
It's scary, noh.
びっくりした... え、これ...
I was startled... Eh, this...
毎回こんなびっくりするの？
Do I get startled like this every time?
もう1回する、のじゃ。
I'll do it again, noh.
アットホームってそういう... 家、家で行われる... てきな？家で行われるゲームのアットホームなのじゃ。
'At-home' means like that... conducted at home... sort of? Games conducted at home are 'at-home', noh.
全パターンでではなれる？
Can I get used to all patterns?
わしの心臓持つ？
Will my heart hold out?
だいぶもう... だいぶ... だいぶバクバク... 行くのじゃ！
It's already quite... quite... quite pounding... Let's go!
はい。
Right.
のじゃ。L、L、L、R、見る。
Noh. L, L, L, R, look.
はい、見る、テレビ。
Right, look, TV.
テレビ鳴ってないじゃん。テレビ載ってないじゃん。
The TV isn't ringing. Nothing's on the TV.
ヒント頂戴。
Give me a hint.
ヒン、あ、来た。ベビーストライクスワットムーブス。
Hin-, ah, it came. 'Baby's strike what moves.'
どういう意味？
What does that mean?
のこぎり！
A chainsaw!
隠れる、隠れる、隠れる、隠れる！
Hide, hide, hide, hide!
うわあああああ！なんでよ、もうなるのじゃ！
Uwaaaaaah! Why, it's happening again, noh!
びっくりした...
I was startled...
あ、動くな言われてたのに隠れたからだめ。
Ah, because I hid even though I was told not to move, no good.
オッケーなのじゃ。パターン、パターン、パターン、パターンね。パターン覚えるのじゃ。
Okay, noh. Pattern, pattern, pattern, pattern. Memorize the pattern, noh.
えーと... えーと... いや、わしとっさの、あのとっさの英語無理、とっさの英語無理、のじゃ。
Umm... Umm... No, I can't do split-second English, I can't do split-second English, noh.
ベ、あ、赤ちゃんが来たら動かない。赤ちゃんが来たら動かない。
Ba-, ah, when the baby comes, don't move. When the baby comes, don't move.
ちょ、おぼ、ねえ、覚えゲーなのにさ、覚えるためにびっくりさせられるのなに？のじゃ。
Hold on, memor-, hey, it's a memory game, so why do I get startled just to memorize it, noh?
4パターン、4パターンだって。えーと、4ならいける、4ならいける。えーと...
Four patterns, four patterns. Umm, if it's four I can do it, if it's four I can do it. Umm...
あの、あ、もう忘れた。なんかジャンプして向こうに行くやつと...
Umm, ah, I forgot already. Something like jumping to go to the other side...
えーと... 止まるやつと...
Umm... the one where you stop...
行くのじゃ！
Let's go, noh!
えっと
Um...
パッパッパッパッて
Quickly, quickly...
あ、のじゃ
Ah, noja...
あ、きた、きた
Ah, here it comes, here it comes!
ベイビー
Baby!
あ、動かない！
Ah, don't move!
動かない！
Don't move!
わしわかる！わしわかる！
I know! I know!
はい動かない！はいお...
Right, don't move! Right, o...
なになになにこわいのやめて！やだ！やだ！ 色なのやめて！見たくないのじゃ！やだやだ！
What is this, stop being scary! No! I don't want to see it! No!
はい消える！
Right, disappear!
はい、動かす！
Right, move!
あ、きた、なんかきた
Ah, something's here.
はい！隠れる！
Right! Hide!
いいじゃない？
Isn't this good?
消えた
It disappeared.
パパヘイトビー、ビーング、見えない
Papa hates being... can't see.
ビーングウォッチ、見られるのが嫌だって、見る
Being watched, they hate being watched—look!
見る、見る、見る、見る、見る、見る、見る、見る
Look, look, look, look, look, look!
お前を！お前を見る！
Look at you! Look at you!
はい消える！
Right, disappear!
ざこおつ！
Trash, gg!
何！？
What!?
え、こ、こうちゃった！ねえ、こうちゃった！あーー！やったー！
Eh, it, it happened! Hey, it happened! Ahh, dammit!
わしやったよ？
Did I do it?
わしうまかったのに！
Even though I did so well!
のじゃー
Noja...
びっくりした
I was startled.
え、でも、こ、凍ったら画面見なきゃいいんじゃない？
Eh, but if it freezes, shouldn't I just not look?
凍ったら、凍ったら画面見なきゃいいんじゃない？
If it freezes, shouldn't I just not look at the screen?
え、これどれぐらいのスコア出すのがすごい？どれぐらいを狙うのじゃ？
Eh, how much score is amazing? How much should I aim for?
これ、きりないよね多分。1時間とかできる人もいるの？
This probably has no end. Can some people do it for an hour?
なんなのじゃ？でもわ、1ミニッツできたよ、1ミニッツ。うん。
What is this? But I made it to 1 minute, 1 minute. Yeah.
40分？40分パスタを叩き続ける
40 minutes? Continuously slapping pasta for 40 minutes...
頭おかしくない？40分
Isn't that crazy? 40 minutes.
正気なのじゃ？パスタを
Are you sane? Pasta...
のじゃ？
Noja?
行くのじゃ！
Let's go!
はい
Right.
はい、ライト、レフト、ライト
Right, right, left, right...
はい
Right.
ライト、ライト、レフト、ライト
Right, right, left, right.
ライト、ライト、レフト、レフト、レフト、レフト
Right, right, left, left, left, left...
ライト、あ
Right, ah...
ステイアウェイフロム
Stay away from...
あ、きた
Ah, it's here.
上手、上手じゃない？
Good, isn't that good?
あ、はやい、はやい！はやくなくない？いける？いけるか？
Ah, fast, fast! Isn't it fast? Can I make it?
はい、いける！
Right, I can!
はい、髪のじゃ！
Right, hair noja!
え、パパ、パパね、パパ
Eh, papa, papa right, papa.
了解？
Got it?
はい見る、見る、見る、見る、見る、見る
Right, look, look, look, look, look, look!
はい、ざこおつ！
Right, trash gg!
ざこおつのじゃ！
Trash gg noja!
見られるのに弱い！
Weak to being watched!
はいはい
Right right.
もう分かったのじゃ、もうこのゲームの攻略法を見つけたのじゃ
I already get it, I've found the strategy for this game!
ベイビー、ベイビーね、オケーオケー
Baby, baby right, okay, okay.
動かない、動かない
Don't move, don't move.
ノームーヴのじゃ！ノームーヴ、ノーパンのぞむのじゃ！ふー！
No move noja! No move, no pants nozomu noja! Whew!
勝った！勝った！
Won! Won!
もう分かった！もうこのゲーム分かったのじゃ
I get it! I already understand this game!
ドンツレッドママスイーユー
Don't let mama see you.
mama ni mirare, e, kore sasuga ni kotchi na no wa
Seen by mama, eh, surely this way is...
はい！
Right!
上手なんじゃない？上手なんじゃない？
Isn't that good? Isn't that good?
上手
Good.
ドントレッドミー
Don't let me...
え、なんかすごい怖い音
Eh, what a really scary sound.
え、なに？
Eh, what?
え、パスタさめっじゃ、ね、パスタさめっじゃ、ね、パスタさめっじゃ、ね、パスタさめっじゃ
Eh, the pasta is getting cold! The pasta is getting cold!
なに！？わー！やだ！
What!? Waah! No!
今のは何？今のは何がわかったのじゃ？
What was that? What did I even figure out just now?
パパも来てた
Papa came too.
え、ど、同時？同時ってあり？ね、同時ってなし！同時はズル！
Eh, simultaneous? Is simultaneous a thing? No, simultaneous is cheating!
同時をズルなのは、だって赤ちゃんと同時に来たら動けないじゃん！
Simultaneous is cheating, because if it comes with the baby, you can't move!
指示変わってる？
Did the instructions change?
わしが隠れたい間にママが消えて
While I wanted to hide, mama disappeared...
あー、し、し、心臓が！心臓がバクバクして…
Ah, my heart... My heart is pounding...
これ、ジャンプ好きやの通れもん…なのかな？
Is this... like a jump-scare game?
これ、慣れる気がしませんのじゃ。
I don't think I'll ever get used to this.
ちょ、トースターでダメなんじゃよ、ワシ。
Wait, the toaster doesn't work for me, you know.
行くのじゃ。
Let's go.
よいしょ、パスタ冷めちゃう。
Let's see, the pasta is getting cold.
上手、上手。上手。
Good, good. Good.
よし。ベイビー、ベイビー、止まる！止まる！止まる、止まる！止まる、止まる！
Alright. Baby, baby, stop! Stop! Stop, stop! Stop, stop!
ベイビー止まる。はい、ベイビー止まる、止まる。上手、上手。パスタ冷めちゃう、消えて！
Baby, stop. Yes, baby, stop, stop. Good, good. Pasta is getting cold, disappear!
パパ、パパね。
Papa, Papa right.
はい、見る！
Yes, look!
はい、女の子と目が合わせられないのじゃ！
Yes, I can't look a girl in the eye!
Don't let mama see, okay?
おーい！
Hey!
いるー！
There!
え、パパの音しない？
Wait, don't you hear Papa?
パパの音しない？
Don't you hear Papa?
パパの音する。見る、見る、見る、見る。お前、見てる、見てる、見てるのじゃ、見てるのじゃ。
I hear Papa. Look, look, look, look. Hey, you're looking, you're looking, you're looking, you're looking.
はいはいはいはい。
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
何？
What?
なんかいる！うわー、いる、いる、いる！
Something's there! Aah, it's there, it's there!
足音来たら、飛び越える！
Ah, when footsteps come, jump across!
え、ねえ、テレビにヒントなかったよ？
Wait, hey, wasn't there a hint on TV?
ねえ、テレビに、テレビにヒントなかった！
Hey, on TV, there was no hint on TV!
ねえ、テレビにヒントなかった。え？
Hey, there was no hint on TV. Huh?
それも、そんなのあり？ね、そんなのなし。
Is that even a thing? Hey, that's not fair.
テレビ途中で消える？言ってよ！
The TV turns off halfway? Tell me!
テレビチュートリアル？
Is the TV a tutorial?
テレビ見てればいっか、って思ってたじゃ。え、じゃあ、赤ちゃんどうするの？赤ちゃんどうするのじゃ？
I thought it'd be fine just watching the TV. Wait, then what about the baby? What about the baby?
赤ちゃん無理。ね、赤ちゃんって、のじゃ。
Baby is impossible. Hey, baby... of all things.
感覚く、音？
Sensation, sound?
え、じゃあもう赤ちゃんの音を覚えるしかない。
Uh, then I have no choice but to learn the baby's sound.
あの、あの、駆け寄ってきたら飛び越えるのは分かって、
Um, I know that when it runs up, I jump across,
なんか低い音がしたら、あの、見、見るのは分かって、
and if a low sound plays, um, I know to look,
ママの音がおかんない。ママと赤ちゃんの音がわかんない。
I don't know Mama's sound. I don't know Mama's and the baby's sound.
赤ちゃんはキャハハって音。ちょ、ちゃんとそれを聞こう？
The baby makes a "hehehe" sound. Wait, let's listen closely to that?
聞く余裕ないのじゃ！
I don't have the leeway to listen!
怖いのよ！
It's scary!
のじゃ、音ゲー？これ音ゲーか？
Is this a rhythm game?
ライトライトレフト…
Right, right, left...
Don't let mama...
あ、ママの声覚えよ。
Ah, let's memorize Mama's voice.
ママの声覚えよ。
Let's memorize Mama's voice.
おお、おばけえ、みたいなこと言ってるのじゃ。おばけえ、みたいなこと言ってる。
Oh, it's a ghost, or something like that it's saying. It's saying something like a ghost.
え？いるやん。
Huh? It's right there.
ん？いないやん。
Hmm? It's not there.
のじゃ？何？ガチ。
What? Seriously?
Papa hates, okay?
Papaね。
Papa, right.
パパね。
パパはそんな怖くない。
Papa isn't that scary.
だって見ればいい。ほら。
Because you just have to watch. Look.
Don't look at meって言ってる。
It's saying "Don't look at me."
いやなこと言ってんだ。
It's saying awful things.
Don't look at meって言ってる。
It's saying "Don't look at me."
ベイビーね？
Baby, right?
ベイビーの方も覚えよ。
Let's memorize the baby's side too.
あはは。
Ahaha.
あはは、って言ってる。
It's saying "Ahaha."
え、これが消える音？
Eh, is this the sound it disappears on?
Stay away from...あ、来た。
Stay away from... ah, it's here.
はいはいはい。シュッて落としたら、ステイアウェイフロムの何とかかな？
Right, right, right. If you drop it with a whoosh, is it 'Stay Away From' something?
のじゃのじゃ。
Noja, noja.
右、左、左、左、右、右…
Right, left, left, left, right, right...
これ何だっけ？
What was this again?
お化けは隠れる。
Ghosts hide.
どーん。
Boom.
ドント・ルック・アット・ミーが、お、お父さん。
'Don't Look at Me' is, oh, Father.
お父さん、見てるやん。
Father, you're watching.
待って。
Wait.
隠れる。
Hide.
消えたから戻る。
It disappeared, so I'll go back.
温める。
Warm it up.
え、何だっけこいつ？
Wh-What was this guy?
うわっ、なんだ！なんだなんだお前！
Whoa, what! What, what, you!
うん？
Huh?
なんだってそいつ！
What was that guy?!
そいつ何？そいつ何？そいつ何のじゃ？そいつ何のじゃ？
What is that guy? What is that guy? What kind of noja is that?
笑うやつ何だっけ？
What was the laughing one?
何だっけそいつ。
What was that guy?
あ、赤ちゃん？
Ah, baby?
赤ちゃんってあんな終わり方だっけ？
Was the baby's ending like that?
あ、何の敵かわかんなかった。
Ah, I didn't know what kind of enemy it was.
のじゃんか。
It's a noja.
やはり慣れ、慣れなのじゃ。
As expected, it's about getting used to it, noja.
あーなんか驚きが、驚きが麻痺になってきた。
Ah, the surprise, the surprise is becoming numb.
驚き、驚きが麻痺になってきたのじゃ！
Surprise, the surprise is becoming numb, noja!
もう、もう怖くない！さすがに、さすがもういけるのじゃ！
I'm not scared anymore! As expected, I can do this!
ふうー。
Phew.
あ、もう、もう余裕なのじゃ。
Ah, already, it's a breeze, noja.
ホロライブ、ホロライブ担当をさせていただきますのじゃ。
I'll be taking charge of Hololive, noja.
イクラでも、イクラでも、イクラでもいけるのじゃ。
I can go through it however many times, noja.
もう来たのじゃ。毎週やるのじゃホラゲ。
It's here already, noja. I do horror games every week, noja.
毎週ホラゲームして、あの、結局ホラゲって覚えゲーだから、パパね。
Playing horror games every week, horror games are memorization games, Papa.
あの、もうびっくりってね、あの、み、見えてしまったら。
Being startled, if you see it.
もう覚えてしまったら何も怖くないのじゃ。あの、初めて見る驚きが、あの、人間を苦しめている。
Once you remember it, nothing is scary. The surprise of seeing it for the first time torments humans.
サラマンダーを苦しめているだけだから、あの、毎週やってホラゲ全パターン覚えたら、全然怖くないのじゃ。
It just torments salamanders, so if you learn all patterns, it's not scary at all, noja.
うん。
Yeah.
おばけで隠れる。
Hide from the ghost.
毎週ホラゲやって、大切つけるのじゃ。
Play horror games every week and keep it precious, noja.
ベイビーね。
Baby, right?
これが、あ、視界がチカチカ見えたら。
This is, if your vision flickers and you see it.
赤ちゃん？
Baby?
わかった。
I see.
ステイ？オッケー。
Stay? Okay.
逃げる。
Run away.
消える。
Disappear.
のじゃ。
Noja.
え、消えた？
Eh, it disappeared?
なんか間違えたけど消えた。
I messed up, but it disappeared.
ラッキー。
Lucky.
間違えたけど消えたのじゃ。
I messed up, but it disappeared, noja.
お父さん見るのじゃ！
Father, look, noja!
タイミングのじゃセカンド！
Second timing, noja!
のじゃ！
Noja!
あ、もう理解したのじゃ完全に。
Ah, I've understood it completely, noja.
もう覚えちゃったらね、やっぱこういうのって、なんだっけ？赤ちゃん。
Once you remember it, what was it? Baby.
止まる。
Stop.
消える。
Disappear.
え、なんでわしパスタ叩いとるのそれで？
Eh, why am I patting pasta with that?
わしなんでパスタ叩いてるの？
Why am I patting pasta?
これ、な、何をしてらっしゃる方？
Who, what kind of person are you supposed to be?
え、位置違うじゃん。
Eh, the position is different.
ママ、ママあの位置で出なかった。
Mama didn't appear in that position.
あの位置パパしか出なかったのに、違う位置でも生まれてる。
Only Papa appeared there, but it's spawning elsewhere.
位置変わるとこもある？
Are there places where position changes?
ま、でも応用か。
Well, but it's an application.
なんか時間が進むにつれて変わっていく。
Somehow, as time goes on, it changes.
お父さん見る。
Father, look.
お父さん置くね。
I'll put Father down, okay?
あ、間違えた。
Ah, I made a mistake.
間違えたけどなんかここで許される。
I made a mistake, but I'm forgiven here.
なんでじゃ？
Why is that, noja?
なんがか分からないけど。
I don't really know, but...
なんか、体格に飛ばなくてもいいっぽい。
It seems like I don't need to jump by height.
なんじゃ？
What's this?
なんだだか。
Why is that?
許され。
Forgive me.
謎。
A mystery.
のじゃ、頭がおかしくなってくるのじゃ。
My head is starting to feel weird.
わしは何を
What am I...
なんだっけ？
What was it?
はいど。
Hide.
消える。
Disappear.
え、なんか体格じゃなくていいじゃん、ぜんぜん。
Wait, it doesn't need to be by height at all, does it?
なんで？
Why?
ねぇ、パスタ難しい。
Hey, pasta is difficult.
ね、パスタがむずい。
Hey, pasta is hard.
パスタがむずい。
Pasta is hard.
パスタがむずいのじゃ。
Pasta is difficult.
パスタ、こう、こうじゃ。
Pasta, like this, like this.
音ゲー、音ゲー、自信なし。
Rhythm game, rhythm game, no confidence.
どうじゃ！
How's that?!
わかってたのに…
Even though I knew...
ひだり…のじゃ…
Left... I see...
え、も怖くない。ね、も怖くない。
Wait, I'm not scared. Hey, I'm not scared.
右目に目のゲージがある。ね、目のゲージは、どういう仕組みなのじゃ？
There's an eye gauge on the right eye. Hey, how does the eye gauge work?
右目のゲージたまると終わっちゃう？
Does it end when the right eye gauge fills up?
え、なんで？え、どうし？見られたら増える？
Huh, why? Huh, what? Does it increase if you're seen?
え、じゃあ、見られちゃダメ？え、じゃあずっと隠れてれば良くない？あ、そしたらパスタが温められない。
Huh, then you shouldn't stay hidden? Wait, wouldn't it be fine to just stay hidden? Ah, but then the pasta won't heat up.
むずい…むずいのじゃ。
It's difficult... so difficult.
ね、汗かいてきた。ね、パスタ、ね、パスタ温めしてたら汗かいてきたんじゃけど。
Hey, I'm starting to sweat. Hey, warming up the pasta made me sweat.
難しいのじゃ。
It's difficult.
え、でもゲームわかってきた。
Well, I'm starting to understand the game.
最後に1回やるのじゃ。最後に1回やる、やらせていただきますのじゃ。
I'll do it one last time. Let me do it one last time.
隠れてるやつで見られるとゲージがカンストしちゃう。隠れる場所も大事ってことか。
If you're spotted while hiding, the gauge maxes out. So the hiding spot matters too.
パスタじゃなくて、わしが温まってきたちょ。わしが温まってきたちょ。
Not the pasta, I'm the one getting warmed up.
5分目指すのじゃ。自分を超える。5分を目指しますのじゃ。
I'll aim for 5 minutes. Surpassing myself. I'll aim for 5 minutes.
行くのじゃー！
Here I go!
急にドーンっていうのもね、怖いから嫌。
I hate sudden loud bangs because they're scary.
怖いからやめてほしい。
They're scary, so I want you to stop.
けっこう、あの、サラマンダーは…
The salamander is...
音と光に弱くて…
Weak to sound and light...
だからなんかその、あんまり音とか光で衝撃を与えないで欲しくて…
So I don't want to shock it too much with sound and light...
で、しかもさ、ホラゲって音もさ、光もさ、両方でさ、怖がらせてくるからさ。
And besides, in horror games, both sound and light scare you.
怖い。
Scary.
See you.
STAND UP
え、まだいる？
Wait, is it still there?
まだいる、まだいる、まだいる。
Still there, still there, still there.
気づかなかった。まだいて笑った。
I didn't notice. I laughed that it was still there.
消える音わかんない、パパね。
I don't know the disappearing sound, Papa.
消える音わかんないのじゃ。
I don't know the disappearing sound.
ドントルックアットミー、アイ、ルックユー、ウォッチ、ウォッチ。
Don't look at me, I look you, watch, watch.
なんか3回入れてくると、2回で終わる時がある。あれ何なのじゃ？
Sometimes when it puts in 3 times, it ends in 2 times. What's that?
STAY AWAYよ。
Stay away.
え、待って、今のずる、今のずる。え、わかった、今何が起きたかわかった。
Wait, that's cheating. I figured out what just happened.
2連続で出た。2連出た。2連出た。2連出たのじゃ。2連出た。
It came out twice in a row. It came out twice.
2連出て…ってことは、越えて越えなきゃいけなかったんだ。越えて越えなきゃいけなくて…
Coming out twice... means I had to go past and past...
そんなの知らないのじゃ。来たら超えなきゃいけないのか。
I didn't know that. So when it comes, I have to cross over.
うーん、それを知らなかったのじゃ。
Hmm, I didn't know that.
難しかった。
It was difficult.
おしまい、おしまいなのじゃ。
It's over, it's over.
怖かったのじゃ！
That was so scary!
もうあの、息が浅くて浅くて仕方ないのじゃ。
My breathing was so shallow I couldn't help it.
のじゃー…
Noja...
おしまいなのじゃ。ちょ、戻るのじゃ。雑談の
It's over. Wait, let's go back. To the chat...
雑談のシーンに戻りましょうのじゃ。今日、今日わしかなり頑張ったんじゃない？
Let's return to the chat scene. Didn't I work pretty hard today?
結構、結構頑張ったんじゃない？
Didn't I work pretty hard?
すごい、すごい怖かったよわし。
I was so, so scared.
ねえ、わしすごい怖かったんだからね。
Hey, I was really scared, you know.
ちなみに、なんか怖かったんだからね。なんか
By the way, I was so scared. Like...
しかもなんか、パスタ叩いてたし。パスタ叩いてたし。
And on top of that, I was hitting pasta. Hitting pasta.
あれ、何、何をやらされてたのじゃガチで。何なのだじゃこのゲーム。
Wait, what on earth was I forced to do? What is this game?
このゲーム、何、何？このゲーム何？
This game, what, what? What is this game?
このゲーム何ガチ？
What is this game, seriously?
のじゃ。え、吹雪先パイさ、新人りゲームくれるなんて優しい先輩って思ったけれど
Noja. Eh, Fubuki-senpai, I thought she was such a kind senior to give a game to a newcomer, but...
なんか、狐に騙されたってこれのことなのじゃ。化け狐でしょのじゃ。
It's like, being deceived by a fox is what this means. A monster fox, right, noja.
化け狐とか良くないか先輩に失礼いたしましたのじゃ。今のなしでお願いしますのじゃ。
Calling her a monster fox is disrespectful to my senior. Please pretend I didn't say that.
あの言葉の、言葉のあやでさ。あの、や、いい先輩なのはわかっておりますのじゃ。
It's just a figure of speech. I know she's a great senior.
あの、や、優しい先輩なのはすごいわかっておりますのじゃ。優しく、優しく声をかけていただいてますのじゃ。
I really know she's a kind senior. She speaks to me so kindly.
のじゃ、あの、のじゃ、あの、吹雪先先輩のファンの人、あの、違いますのじゃ。すごい良くて、優しくって、優しい先輩だと
Noja, um, noja, um, Fubuki-senpai's fans, um, that's not it. She's so good, kind, and...
どうだ？どうじゃ？いや、
How is it? How is it? No...
でもわし、わしホラー嫌いなの知ってる？ねえ、わし、わしホラー、わしホラー怖がってるの知ってるのにさ、なんかホラーですみたいなかかないでさ、初心者でも安心アットホームなスパゲッティですって書いてるの
But you know I hate horror, right? Hey, you know I'm terrified of horror, yet instead of writing "horror," it says "At-home friendly spaghetti for beginners,"
配信者的 に、のじゃ。
in a streamer kind of way, noja.
え、もしかしてさ、お粥先パイにもゲームいただいたんじゃが、え、なんかタンポポのゲームもそういう系？実話ホラーみたいなちょっと見てないんだけど、どういうのか知らないんだけどさ。
Eh, could it be? I also received a game from Okayu-senpai, um, is the dandelion game that kind of genre too? Actually, it's like horror? I haven't watched it yet, so I don't know what it's like.
え、これからもし先パイから送られてきてるゲーム全部、ホラーの可能性ありの心で、ホラー、ホラーの可能性ありみたいな心で挑まなきゃいけないの？
Eh, does that mean all the games sent from senpai from now on have to be approached with the mindset that they might be horror?
来週やろうと思ってたんだけど、タンポポ、一応そのつもりで挑みますのじゃ。
I was planning to do it next week, but dandelion, I'll approach it with that in mind, noja.
そのつもりで挑みますのじゃ。のじゃ。
I'll approach it with that in mind, noja. Noja.
怖かったー！恐ろしかったー！
That was scary! That was terrifying!
しかもなんかパスタ叩いてる間さ、パスタ叩いてる間さ、あの将棋を保つためにさ、適当に喋ってたらなんかホラー毎週やるみたいなこと言っちゃった。
And besides, while hitting pasta, while hitting pasta, to keep my composure, if I talked casually and accidentally said I'll play horror every week...
なんかできないことはやれる、やるって言っちゃダメ！みたいな
Like, you shouldn't say you can do things you can't!
お、およそ、およそ毎週やるとかにするか。
Oh, I guess I'll make it around playing every week or something.
あ、なんか、なんだけっけ？あの、8番出口の続編みたいなあるじゃろ？あれ、あれ気になってたから
Ah, what was it? You know, like the sequel to The Exit 8? I was curious about that, so...
やってみようかな来週。ちょ、毎週かはあれだけど。
I might try it next week. Well, not necessarily every week.
ま、毎週かはあれだけど、一旦来週もやってみようかの。
Well, not every week, but I'll try it next week once.
一旦ね。ちょっとや、やってみようかな。
Once, yeah. Let's try it out a bit.
およそ、あの、あの、あの個人差あり。
Roughly, um, um, there are individual differences.
あの、あの週休2日と週休2日制的な感じで、あの、あの1日しか休めないみたいな、そう、跨がってる可能性あり。
Um, like a two-day weekend vs. a five-day work week, where you can only rest one day, so there's a possibility it overlaps.
そう、みたいな感じにしよう。そう、そういう感じにするのじゃ。
Yeah, let's make it feel like that. Yeah, let's do it like that, noja.
完全週休2日じゃないやつ、そう、そうそうそうそう、完全じゃない系の、それぐらいの認識でやるのじゃ、うん。
The ones that aren't fully two-day weekends, yeah, yeah, yeah, doing it with that level of recognition, yeah.
え、これチャンネルって送っていいの？
Eh, can I send this to the channel?
送るなら絶対綴りだけど、綴りもらってって聞いたのじゃ。
If I send it, I definitely need the spelling, but I heard I'm getting the spelling!
づづりもらってるって聞いたから
I heard you got a tsuzuri...
ちょ、なんか、あのギフト機能が解放されてない可能性があって
Wait, like, that gift feature might not have been unlocked yet.
我々、我々が新人に付き
Like, when we take on newbies...
うん。
Yeah.
から、ちょっとその機能とかを確認しつつ検討させていただきますなのじゃ。
So I'll check those functions and consider it, nanoja.
うん。なので
Yeah. So...
感謝の気持ちを込めてきょーこに、まあ確かにきょーこに送っても
with gratitude to Kyoko—well, true, even if I send it to Kyoko,
きょーこは、なんか、1時間とかやりできそうだしな。
Kyoko could probably do it for an hour or so.
ありだなのじゃ。
That works, nanoja.
うん。なので
Yeah. So...
念のため確認してみるのじゃ。
I'll double-check just in case.
はあ、びっくりした。
Phew, I was surprised.
わかった。
I see.
ちょ、なんか、あのミスってなんか画面映しちゃったとこ、まりちゃんに聞いてみるのじゃ。
Wait, I'll ask Mari-chan about where I accidentally showed the screen by mistake.
これ、あのアーカイブ残していい？って聞いてみる。
I'll ask her, "Is it okay to leave this archive up?"
うん。
Yeah.
多分、多分そんな、やばいものは映してないと思うけど。
I probably didn't show anything super bad, but
念のため確認してみるのじゃ。
I'll check just in case.
のじゃ。
Nanoja.
明日はリズム天国で遊べますのじゃ！
Tomorrow we'll play Rhythm Heaven, nanoja!
うん。で、明後日は、ま、マシュマロ雑談をしようと思ってて。
Yeah. And the day after tomorrow, well, I thought I'd do marshmallow chatting.
ま、マシュマロ雑談をしようと思ってるから、えっと、
So, since I want to do marshmallow chatting, um,
TwitterにマシュマロのURLを貼ってるから、質問を募集しておりますのじゃ！
I've posted the marshmallow URL on Twitter, so we're taking questions, nanoja!
お願いしますのじゃ！え、もしかして明日のリズム天国に備えて今日音ゲーの練習してた？
Please! Oh, wait, were you practicing rhythm games today to prepare for tomorrow's Rhythm Heaven?
そういうこと？そういうことなのじゃ？
Is that it? Is that what it was, nanoja?
まだ受け付けておりますのじゃ！エゴサよりいっぱい集まるから
We're still accepting them, nanoja! They gather even more than ego-searching,
見るの楽しいのじゃ。
so it's fun to look at, nanoja.
全部配信で読めないんだけど、ちゃんと見させていただいておりますのじゃ。
I can't read all of them on stream, but I get to read through them properly, nanoja.
ありがとうのじゃ！
Thank you, nanoja!
じゃあ、明日、え、19時からリズム天国配信で
Well then, tomorrow, um, starting at 7 PM, we'll have a Rhythm Heaven stream,
お会いしましょうのじゃ。
let's meet then, nanoja.
スケジュールも明日のおうちに出したいなって思ってるのでお待ちくださいのじゃ！
I'm thinking of putting out the schedule tomorrow too, so please look forward to it, nanoja!
えや、いらっしゃい。今日の配信はおしまいなのですのじゃ！
Hey, welcome. Today's stream is over, nanoja!
また、明日の配信でお会いしましょう！さらはちゃー！
Let's meet again in tomorrow's stream! Bye-bye!
リズム天国…明日リズム天国で遊びますのじゃ！
Rhythm Heaven... Tomorrow we'll play Rhythm Heaven, nanoja!
TwitterにマシュマロのURLを貼ってるからね
I've posted the marshmallow URL on Twitter, so
質問を募集しておりますのじゃ！お願いしまーすのじゃ！
we're taking questions, nanoja! Please, nanoja!
もしかして明日のリズム天国に備えて今日音ゲーの練習してた？そういうこと？
Were you practicing rhythm games today to prepare for tomorrow's Rhythm Heaven? Is that it?
そういうことなのじゃ？まだ受け付けておりますのじゃ！
Is that what it was, nanoja? We're still accepting them, nanoja!
エゴサよりいっぱい集まるから、見るの楽しいのじゃ！
They gather even more than ego-searching, so it's fun to look at, nanoja!
全部配信で読めないんだけど、ちゃんと見させていただいておりますのじゃ！
I can't read all of them on stream, but I get to read through them properly, nanoja!
ありがとうのじゃ！いっぱいマシュマロ届いて嬉しいのじゃ！
Thank you, nanoja! I'm so happy so many marshmallows arrived, nanoja!
じゃあ明日、19時からリズム天国配信でお会いしましょうのじゃ！
Well then, let's meet tomorrow at 7 PM for the Rhythm Heaven stream, nanoja!
スケジュールも明日のおうちに出したいなって思ってるのでお待ちくださいのじゃ！
I'm thinking of putting out the schedule tomorrow too, so please wait for it, nanoja!
今日はね、もう、明日、明後日はマシュマロ雑談をしようと思ってて…
Today, well, tomorrow and the day after I thought I'd do marshmallow chatting...
マシュマロ雑談をしようと思ってるから、TwitterにURLを貼ってるのじゃ！
Since I want to do marshmallow chatting, I posted the URL on Twitter, nanoja!
たくさんの質問、お待ちしておりますのじゃ！今日の配信はおしまいなのですのじゃ！
We look forward to lots of questions, nanoja! Today's stream is over, nanoja!
また明日の配信でお会いしましょう！さらばじゃー！
Let's meet again in tomorrow's stream! Farewell, nanoja!